<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- **************************************************************************
     *                                                                        *
     *    (C) Copyright Paul Mensonides 2003-2004.                            *
     *                                                                        *
     *    Distributed under the Boost Software License, Version 1.0.          *
     *    (See accompanying file LICENSE).                                    *
     *                                                                        *
     *    See http://chaos-pp.sourceforge.net for the most recent version.    *
     *                                                                        *
     ************************************************************************** -->

<header name="chaos/preprocessor/recursion/revive.h" author="Paul Mensonides" date="2003-2004">
<overview>
	The <self/> header defines a macro used to re-enable a macro name that was previously disabled (i.e. "painted blue").
</overview>

<macro id="REVIVE">
	<abstract>
		The <REVIVE/> macro re-enables a macro name preprocessing token that was previously disabled.
	</abstract>
	<usage>
		<syntax><REVIVE/>(macro)</syntax>
		<param id="macro">
			The macro name to be re-enabled.
			This macro name must have a derivative form suffixed with <code>_ID</code> that is a nullary macro that expands to <var>macro</var> (i.e. an indirection macro).
		</param>
	</usage>
	<para>
		This macro concatenates <code>_ID</code> to <var>macro</var> and invokes the result with nullary parentheses.
		<snippet>
			<PRIMITIVE_CAT/>(macro, _ID)()
		</snippet>
		It is intended that an appropriate indirection macro exists for <var>macro</var>.
		For example, assuming that <var>macro</var> is <code>ABC</code>, then <code>ABC_ID()</code> should expand to <code>ABC</code>.
	</para>
	<para>
		Macro name preprocessing tokens get permanently disabled when they are created in (or just pass through) the context created by the macro to which they refer.
		Even when a disabled macro name is no longer inside that context, it remains disabled--permanently.
		Hence, the creation of a new preprocessing token is required, which is what <REVIVE/> does through concatenation and an indirection macro.
		Note that if a macro name preprocessing token is "revived" when the context is still present, it will just immediately get disabled again.
		Consequently, this macro is <em>not</em> a substitute for recursion.
	</para>
	<listing>
		#include <chaos-preprocessor-facilities-expand.h/>
		#include <chaos-preprocessor-recursion-revive.h/>
		
		<EXPAND/>(<EXPAND/>)(++) // <EXPAND/>(++)
		
		<REVIVE/>(
		    <EXPAND/>(<EXPAND/>)
		)(++)
		// ++
		
		#define ABC(x) x
		#define ABC_ID() ABC
		
		ABC(ABC)(--)                  // ABC(--)
		<REVIVE/>(ABC(ABC))(--) // --
	</listing>
	<derivative id="REVIVE_ID"/>
	<derivative id="REVIVE_" lang="C99"/>
</macro>

</header>
