<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<header name="chaos/preprocessor/facilities/as_args.h" author="Paul Mensonides" date="2003-2004">
<overview>
	The <self/> header defines a facility used to map an <link id="array"/> to individual arguments in invocations of user-defined macros by library algorithms.
</overview>

<macro id="AS_ARGS">
	<abstract>
		The <AS_ARGS/> macro is used to map an <link id="array"/> to individual arguments in invocations of user-defined macros by library algorithms.
	</abstract>
	<usage>
		<syntax><AS_ARGS/>(n)</syntax>
		<param id="n">
			The arity of the library algorithm target macro.
			Valid values range from <code>2</code> to <LIMIT_AS_ARGS/>.
		</param>
	</usage>
	<para>
		This macro may be used with every library algorithm that allows a user-defined macro to expand to a <link id="deferred expression"/> and contains a state or auxiliary data argument.
		These algorithms also allow a double user-specified operation as a macro name (i.e. a non-<link id="λ expression"/>) of the following form:
		<snippet>
			B A
		</snippet>
		The <code>A</code> macro is invoked as normal but expands to the argument list for the invocation of <code>B</code>.
		An invocation of the <AS_ARGS/> macro plays the role of <code>A</code> against some user-specified macro <code>B</code>.
	</para>
	<para>
		The function of this macro is to produce a macro of arity <var>n</var> that transforms the argument list that it is passed by incrementing its first argument (<var>s</var>) and converting its last argument (a state or auxiliary data argument) from an <link id="array"/> to a comma-separated list of arguments:
		<snippet>
			(s, (2, (x, y)))       // (<NEXT/>(s), x, y)
			(s, p, (3, (a, b, c))) // (<NEXT/>(s), p, a, b, c)
		</snippet>
		This minimizes the amount of data structure access that is necessary when variadic arguments cannot be used.
	</para>
	<listing>
		#include <chaos-preprocessor-arithmetic-dec.h/>
		#include <chaos-preprocessor-arithmetic-inc.h/>
		#include <chaos-preprocessor-array-elem.h/>
		#include <chaos-preprocessor-control-while.h/>
		#include <chaos-preprocessor-facilities-as_args.h/>
		#include <chaos-preprocessor-logical-bool.h/>
		#include <chaos-preprocessor-recursion-expr.h/>
		
		#define ADD(x, y) \
		    <ARRAY_ELEM/>(0, <EXPR/>(<WHILE/>( \
		        ADD_P <AS_ARGS/>(2), \
		        ADD_O <AS_ARGS/>(2), \
		        (2, (x, y)) \
		    ))) \
		    /**/
		#define ADD_P(s, x, y) <BOOL/>(y)
		#define ADD_O(s, x, y) \
		    (2, (<INC/>(x), <DEC/>(y))) \
		    /**/
		
		ADD(4, 5) // 9
	</listing>
	<derivative id="AS_ARGS_ID"/>
	<derivative id="AS_ARGS_" lang="C99"/>
</macro>

</header>
