<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- **************************************************************************
     *                                                                        *
     *    (C) Copyright Paul Mensonides 2003-2004.                            *
     *                                                                        *
     *    Distributed under the Boost Software License, Version 1.0.          *
     *    (See accompanying file LICENSE).                                    *
     *                                                                        *
     *    See http://chaos-pp.sourceforge.net for the most recent version.    *
     *                                                                        *
     ************************************************************************** -->

<document id="Active Arguments" author="Paul Mensonides" date="2003-2004">
	<section>
		<para>
			An <link id="active argument"/> is an argument that expands each time that it is scanned by the preprocessor.
			For example,
			<snippet>
				#define A(n) \
				    <DEFER/>(A_INDIRECT)()(<INC/>(n)) \
				    /**/
				#define A_INDIRECT() A
				
				#define X(arg) arg
				#define Y(arg) X(arg)
				#define Z(arg) Y(arg)
				
				   A(0)   // A_INDIRECT()(1)
				X( A(0) ) // A_INDIRECT()(2)
				Y( A(0) ) // A_INDIRECT()(3)
				Z( A(0) ) // A_INDIRECT()(4)
			</snippet>
			In the above, each invocation of <code>A</code> is subjected to a different number of scans, which causes the results to be different each time.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Terminal State">
		<para>
			Normally, unlike the example in the previous section, an <link id="active argument"/> eventually reaches a terminal, or inactive, state.
			For example,
			<snippet>
				#define B(n) \
				    n <WHEN/>(n)( \
				        B_INDIRECT <OBSTRUCT/>()()(<DEC/>(n)) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				#define B_INDIRECT() B
				
				#define ID(x) x
				
				#define SCAN(x) ID(ID(ID(ID(ID(x)))))
				
				SCAN( B(0) ) // 0
				SCAN( B(1) ) // 1 0
				SCAN( B(2) ) // 2 1 0
				SCAN( B(3) ) // 3 2 1 0
			</snippet>
			Here, each invocation of <code>B</code> creates an <link id="active argument"/> that eventually reaches a terminal state.
			However, each invocation reaches that terminal state at a different time (i.e. after a different number of scans).
		</para>
		<para>
			Not all useful <link id="active arguments"/> reach a terminal state.
			The following code produces an infinite <link id="list"/>:
			<snippet>
				#define HEAD(list) HEAD_I list
				#define HEAD_I(head, tail) head
				
				#define TAIL(list) TAIL_I list
				#define TAIL_I(head, tail) tail
				
				#define STREAM(x, op, data) (x, STREAM_I(x, op, data))
				#define STREAM_INDIRECT() STREAM_I
				#define STREAM_I(x, op, data) \
				    <IIF/>(<IS_NULLARY/>(TAIL_I(~, ())))( \
				        STREAM_INDIRECT <OBSTRUCT/>()()(x, op, data) \
				            <TUPLE_EAT/>(3), \
				        STREAM_II \
				    )(op(x, data), op, data) \
				    /**/
				#define STREAM_II(x, op, data) \
				    (x, <DEFER/>(STREAM_INDIRECT)()(x, op, data)) \
				    /**/
				
				#define NATURALS STREAM(0, NATURALS_OP, ~)
				#define NATURALS_OP(x, _) <INC/>(x)
				
				HEAD(NATURALS)             // 0
				HEAD(TAIL(NATURALS))       // 1
				HEAD(TAIL(TAIL(NATURALS))) // 2
			</snippet>
			The <code>NATURALS</code> macro conceptually expands to a <link id="list"/> of all natural numbers.
			(Because this code is using <link id="saturation arithmetic"/>, the value eventually will reach <LIMIT_MAG/>, causing an infinite <link id="list"/> of values <link id="saturated"/> to <LIMIT_MAG/> from that point on.)
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Multiple Dimensions">
		<para>
			The preprocessor's "normal" scanning can be considered the first dimension of activity.
			An argument passed in a macro invocation is scanned in what can be considered the second dimension of activity.
			Typically, this initial argument scan simply expands to a terminal result.
			This behavior is so typical, in fact, and has no effect on encapsulation (unless the argument is used as an operand of <code>#</code> or <code>##</code>), that it is not enough to be considered an <link id="active argument"/>.
			When an initial argument scan <em>does not</em> expand to a terminal result, that argument can properly be called an <link id="active argument"/>.
		</para>
		<para>
			All of the uses of <link id="active arguments"/> that have been considered so far have been <link id="active"/> in the second dimension.
			These can be called first-level <link id="active arguments"/>.
			However, <link id="active arguments"/> themselves invoke other macros, possibly passing arguments.
			Those arguments are scanned in a higher dimension yet--yielding third, fourth, and fifth (and so on) dimensions of scanning and, therefore, second-, third-, and fourth-level (etc.) <link id="active arguments"/>.
			A second-level <link id="active argument"/> occurs, for example, when a first-level <link id="active argument"/> invokes a macro with an <link id="active argument"/>.
			The <code>STREAM</code> macro defined in the previous section has a parameter intended to be used as auxiliary data.
			If an <link id="active argument"/> is passed as the auxiliary data, it effectively becomes a second-level <link id="active argument"/>.
			The following code demonstrates this:
			<snippet>
				#define SCANS STREAM(0, SCANS_OP, <DELVE/>())
				#define SCANS_OP(x, d) <HALT/>(d)
				
				HEAD(TAIL(TAIL(TAIL(SCANS))))
			</snippet>
			(The result isn't shown here because the generated elements are the number of scans endured by the auxiliary data argument at the point when the element is created.
			That number of scans is not guaranteed to be a specific value by the library.
			However, each element <em>will</em> have a value that is some magnitude <em>higher</em> than the previous element.)
			In this example, the <link id="active argument"/> constructed by <code>SCANS</code> is scanned repeatedly as it passes through <code>HEAD</code> and <code>TAIL</code>.
			Each of those scans causes invocations that pass the auxiliary data--which is itself <link id="active"/>.
			The following example uses multi-level <link id="active arguments"/> more explicitly:
			<snippet>
				#define A(n) \
				    <WHEN/>(n)( \
				        A_INDIRECT <OBSTRUCT/>()()(<DEC/>(n)) \
				        n \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				#define A_INDIRECT() A
				
				#define I(x) x
				
				( I(I(I(I(I( A(3) ))))) ) // ( 1 2 3 )
				
				#define B(n) \
				    <WHEN/>(n)( \
				        B_INDIRECT <OBSTRUCT/>()()(<DEC/>(n)) \
				        ( I(I(I(I(I( A(n) ))))) ) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				#define B_INDIRECT() B
				
				#define J(x) x
				
				( J(J(J(J(J( B(3) ))))) ) // ( ( 1 ) ( 1 2 ) ( 1 2 3 ) )
				
				#define C(n) \
				    <WHEN/>(n)( \
				        C_INDIRECT <OBSTRUCT/>()()(<DEC/>(n)) \
				        ( J(J(J(J(J( B(n) ))))) ) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				#define C_INDIRECT() C
				
				#define K(x) x
				
				( K(K(K(K(K( C(3) ))))) )
				// ( ( ( 1 ) ) ( ( 1 ) ( 1 2 ) ) ( ( 1 ) ( 1 2 ) ( 1 2 3 ) ) )
			</snippet>
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Library Support">
		<para>
			In the infinite <link id="list"/> example, notice the use of the custom <code>HEAD</code> and <code>TAIL</code> macros instead of the <LIST_HEAD/> and <LIST_TAIL/> library primitives.
			This replication is purposeful.
			Except in a very few situations, the library currently is not designed to handle user input that contains <link id="active arguments"/> that invoke library primitives.
			Therefore, <link id="active arguments"/>, unless directly constructed by library primitives, should never be passed to library primitives.
			The reason for this restriction is that library primitives often internally use other library primitives.
			If an <link id="active argument"/>, using a specific library primitive, passes through that same primitive, the usage of that primitive inside the <link id="active argument"/> will fail to expand.
			This failure can cause unexpected results or even compilation errors.
			The library primitives that any given library primitive uses internally are implementation details that are not documented and should not be considered stable.
			Therefore, there is no guarantee that a library primitive that is used by an <link id="active argument"/> is not also used by a library primitive to which the <link id="active argument"/> is passed.
			The following illustrates such behavior:
			<snippet>
				#define BUILD(n) BUILD_I(<INC/>(n), n)
				#define BUILD_I(n, r) \
				    <DEFER/>(BUILD_INDIRECT)()( \
				        <INC/>(n), <PRIMITIVE_CAT/>(r, n) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				#define BUILD_INDIRECT() BUILD_I
				
				#define ID(x) x
				
				ID(ID(ID( BUILD(1) ))) // BUILD_INDIRECT()( 6, 12345 )
				
				<CAT/>(BUILD(1) x, y) // failure!
			</snippet>
			Here, the <link id="active argument"/> constructed by <code>BUILD(1)</code> passes through <CAT/>.
			The <CAT/> macro happens to pass its arguments on to <PRIMITIVE_CAT/> internally which causes the <link id="active argument"/> to pass through <PRIMITIVE_CAT/>.
			This, in turn, causes the use of <PRIMITIVE_CAT/> in the <link id="active argument"/> to fail to expand--causing an unexpected garbage result.
			This is a simplistic example where it is relatively easy to figure out what went wrong, but that is not always the case.
		</para>
		<para>
			There are a few library primitives that intentionally construct <link id="active arguments"/>.
			The most common of these are <DEFER/>, <OBSTRUCT/>, and other macros that simply delay invocation of a macro through some number of scans.
			Other examples include <DELVE/> and <RAIL/>.
			In general, the library is designed to handle these <link id="active arguments"/> provided that the specific library primitive used does not require the argument to be in a specific form.
			For example, passing an <link id="active argument"/> to <INC/> is invalid because <INC/> requires a number between <code>0</code> and <LIMIT_MAG/>, and an <link id="active argument"/> is not a number.
			On the other hand, <TUPLE_ELEM/> does not require that the elements of the <link id="tuple"/> it is accessing be in any particular form:
			<snippet>
				<HALT/>(
				    <TUPLE_ELEM/>(3, 0, (<DELVE/>(), x, y))
				)
			</snippet>
		</para>
		<para>
			Future versions of the library may support <link id="active arguments"/> more generally.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Postscript">
		<para>
			It is worth noting that an entire recursion engine can be built by the manipulation of <link id="active arguments"/>.
			A simplistic example is demonstrated here (this one uses variadics as a change of pace).
			<snippet>
				#define EVAL(...) \
				    A(A(A(__VA_ARGS__))) \
				    /**/
				#define A(...) B(B(B(__VA_ARGS__)))
				#define B(...) C(C(C(__VA_ARGS__)))
				#define C(...) D(D(D(__VA_ARGS__)))
				#define D(...) E(E(E(__VA_ARGS__)))
				#define E(...) __VA_ARGS__
				
				#define REPEAT(count, macro, ...) \
				    <WHEN/>(count)( \
				        REPEAT_INDIRECT <OBSTRUCT/>()()( \
				            <DEC/>(count), macro, __VA_ARGS__ \
				        ) \
				        macro <OBSTRUCT/>()( \
				            <DEC/>(count), __VA_ARGS__ \
				        ) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				#define REPEAT_INDIRECT() REPEAT
				
				#define PARAM(n, ...) <COMMA_IF/>(n) __VA_ARGS__ ## n
				
				EVAL( REPEAT(100, PARAM, class T) ) // class T0, class T1, ... class T99
				
				#define FIXED(n, ...) <COMMA_IF/>(n) __VA_ARGS__
				#define TTP(n, ...) \
				    <COMMA_IF/>(n) \
				        template&lt;REPEAT(<INC/>(n), FIXED, class)&gt; class __VA_ARGS__ ## n \
				    /**/
				
				EVAL( REPEAT(3, TTP, T) )
				// template&lt;class&gt; class T0,
				// template&lt;class, class&gt; class T1,
				// template&lt;class, class, class&gt; class T2
			</snippet>
			This form of recursion engine, while interesting, has several major drawbacks.
			Most of them can be minimized, in one way or another, but a fundamental problem is efficiency.
			Eventually, the <link id="active argument"/> reaches a terminal state--at which point it no longer changes--and no further scans are required to produce the final result.
			However, further scans are applied anyway--exponentially.
			Another drawback is that this approach effectively enforces a continuation style because it destroys call-and-return semantics.
			In the above example, the result of the "nested" use of <code>REPEAT</code> is not needed for further calculation, so it isn't an issue.
			That is not always the case.
		</para>
		<para>
			(The library uses a form of recursion very similar to this.
			The major difference is that there is no outer controller that applies a massive number of scans to its argument.
			Instead, there is only an identity macro that causes its argument to be scanned twice--where the first scan yields a <link id="deferred"/> use of another identity macro (and so on).
			This creates a cascading effect that terminates when another identity macro is not generated.
			Thus, all activity stops when a particular algorithm completes.)
		</para>
	</section>
</document>
