<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- **************************************************************************
     *                                                                        *
     *    (C) Copyright Paul Mensonides 2003-2004.                            *
     *                                                                        *
     *    Distributed under the Boost Software License, Version 1.0.          *
     *    (See accompanying file LICENSE).                                    *
     *                                                                        *
     *    See http://chaos-pp.sourceforge.net for the most recent version.    *
     *                                                                        *
     ************************************************************************** -->

<document id="Example: Binary Literals" author="Paul Mensonides" date="2003-2004">
	<section>
		<para>
			<em>NOTE: THIS DOCUMENT IS INCOMPLETE.</em>
		</para>
		<para>
			The specification of binary integer values is a common task usually accomplished using hexidecimal literals.
			This is an unnecessary and error-prone indirection between what is intended and what is accomplished.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Runtime Computation">
		<para>
			The simplest method of converting binary literals to values is to perform the conversion at runtime.
			<snippet>
				#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
				#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;
				
				unsigned long binary(const char* x) {
				    unsigned long r = 0;
				    while (*x) (r *= 2) += *x++ - '0';
				    return r;
				}
				
				int main(void) {
				    printf("%lu\n", binary("101010"));
				    return EXIT_SUCCESS;
				}
			</snippet>
			Besides the inefficiency of runtime computation, the major drawback of this approach is that the result cannot be used as a compile-time constant.
		</para>
		<para>
			(On the other hand, the major advantage of this approach is that it <em>can</em> do the computation at runtime--which is important in its own right.
			<snippet>
				int main(int argc, char* argv[]) {
				    if (argc &lt; 2) {
				        return EXIT_FAILURE;
				    }
				    printf("%lu", binary(argv[1]));
				    return EXIT_SUCCESS;
				}
			</snippet>
			Neither template metaprogramming nor preprocessor metaprogramming can achieve that.)
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Template Metaprogramming">
		<para>
			In C++, template metaprogramming can be used to specify binary literals by reinterpreting the value of decimal literal (containing nothing but <code>0</code>'s and <code>1</code>'s).
			<snippet>
				#include &lt;iostream&gt;
				
				template&lt;class T, T V&gt; struct map_integral {
				    static const T value = V;
				};
				
				template&lt;class T, T V&gt; const T map_integral&lt;T, V&gt;::value;
				
				template&lt;unsigned long x&gt; struct binary
				    : map_integral&lt;unsigned long, binary&lt;x / 10&gt;::value &lt;&lt; 1 | x % 10&gt; { };
				
				template&lt;&gt; struct binary&lt;0&gt; : map_integral&lt;unsigned long, 0&gt; { };
				
				int main(void) {
				    std::cout &lt;&lt; binary&lt;11111111&gt;::value &lt;&lt; '\n'; // prints 255
				    return 0;
				}
			</snippet>
		</para>
		<para>
			However, there are a few drawbacks to using the template mechanism for this purpose, the most obvious of which is that this approach can only be used in C++.
			The other drawbacks are more subtle....
		</para>
		<para>
			Integer literals cannot contain enough digits to specify the full range of the greatest-width integer.
			If, for example, an <code>unsigned long</code> is a 32-bit integer, a decimal literal would require thirty-two digits to fully specify each bit--which is well outside the range of a 32-bit integer.
			<snippet>
				binary&lt;10101010101010101010101010101010&gt;::value // error!
			</snippet>
			Thus, in order to specify such a value, the bits must be separated into groups and processed semi-independently.
			The following implementation uses four groups of at most eight bits (note that, for simplicity, the value of a particular bit group isn't checked for overflow):
			<snippet>
				#include &lt;iostream&gt;
				
				template&lt;class T, T V&gt; struct map_integral {
				    static const T value = V;
				};
				
				template&lt;class T, T V&gt; const T map_integral&lt;T, V&gt;::value;
			    
				template&lt;int A, int B = -1, int C = -1, int D = -1&gt; struct binary
				    : map_integral&lt;
				        unsigned long,
				        binary&lt;A, B, C&gt;::value &lt;&lt; 8 | binary&lt;D&gt;::value
				    &gt; { };
				
				template&lt;int A, int B, int C&gt; struct binary&lt;A, B, C&gt;
				    : map_integral&lt;
				        unsigned long,
				        binary&lt;A, B&gt;::value &lt;&lt; 8 | binary&lt;C&gt;::value
				    &gt; { };
				
				template&lt;int A, int B&gt; struct binary&lt;A, B&gt;
				    : map_integral&lt;
				        unsigned long,
				        binary&lt;A&gt;::value &lt;&lt; 8 | binary&lt;B&gt;::value
				    &gt; { };
				
				template&lt;int A&gt; struct binary&lt;A&gt;
				    : map_integral&lt;
				        unsigned long,
				        binary&lt;A / 10&gt;::value &lt;&lt; 1 | A % 10
				    &gt; { };
				
				template&lt;&gt; struct binary&lt;0&gt; : map_integral&lt;unsigned long, 0&gt; { };
				
				int main(void) {
				    std::cout
				        &lt;&lt; binary&lt;11111111&gt;::value                               &lt;&lt; '\n'
				        &lt;&lt; binary&lt;11111111, 11111111&gt;::value                     &lt;&lt; '\n'
				        &lt;&lt; binary&lt;11111111, 11111111, 11111111, 11111111&gt;::value &lt;&lt; '\n';
				    return 0;
				}
			</snippet>
			(With a little help from preprocessor metaprogramming, the boilerplate of this metafunction implementation can be extended to handle (nearly) arbitrary numbers of bit groups.
			However, doing so would probably be overkill, as the greatest-width integer type is unlikely to grow fast (or differ from platform to platform) enough to justify the boilerplate of the preprocessor generation itself.)
		</para>
		<para>
			The reliance on the greatest-width integer type illustrates another drawback of the template-based approach.
			The compiler cannot perform arbitrary-precision arithmetic (at least, not directly).
			As such, there is a (relatively low) limit on the maximum integer width on which the compiler can perform arithmetic.
			This isn't terrible--most results need to be stored in some integer variable anyway.
			Nevertheless, the limitation exists.
		</para>
		<para>
			The most subtle drawback of the template-based approach is that the value of each bit group must be either <code>0</code> or begin with <code>1</code>.
			Otherwise, the literal is treated as octal instead of decimal--which fouls up the entire mechanism:
			<snippet>
				binary&lt;00000010&gt;::value // 8 (not 2)
			</snippet>
			Thus, binary literals cannot be specified (as they typically are) with leading <code>0</code>'s to fill up some specific width.
			That limitation is not only annoying, but is fundamentally error-prone because there is no way to verify the original forms of the input values.
			(One possible solution to this problem is to alter the implementation to expect hexidecimal numbers instead of decimal numbers.
			This would allow leading <code>0</code>'s at the inconvenience of prefixing each value with <code>0x</code> or <code>0X</code>.)
		</para>
		<para>
			Though the implementation can be specified in a number of different ways, these drawbacks are fundamental.
			The second, third, and fourth drawbacks are all the result of a single root issue.
			The above code acts on integral values instead of acting on the literals themselves.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Enter the Preprocessor...">
		<para>
			As it happens, there is a language mechanism that can operate (to a degree) on literal values--macros.
		</para>
		<para>
			Given some data structure of bits (i.e. <code>0</code>'s and <code>1</code>'s), it is relatively easy to calculate a decimal value by accumulating the bits.
			<snippet>
				unsigned long binary(const char* x) {
				    unsigned long r = 0;
				    while (*x) {
				        (r *= 2) += *x++ - '0';
				    }
				    return r;
				}
			</snippet>
			Each time a bit is found, the algorithm doubles the running result and adds the value of the bit.
			Instead of accumulating the elements of a data structure by manually looping (or recursing), a generalized notion of "accumulation" can be used--<code>std::accumulate</code>.
			<snippet>
				#include &lt;cstring&gt;
				#include &lt;numeric&gt;
				
				unsigned long binary(const char* x) {
				    struct local {
				        static unsigned long exec(unsigned long x, char bit) {
				            return x * 2 + (bit - '0');
				        }
				    };
				    return std::accumulate(x, x + std::strlen(x), 0UL, &amp;local::exec);
				}
			</snippet>
			This is a higher-order transformation which yields a design that has greater similarity to a typical preprocessor-based design than the original iterative algorithm.
			Note that the above transformation is actually two transformations.
			The first is the abstraction of looping itself (e.g. the loop body is executed repeatedly until some supplied predicate yields <code>false</code>).
			The second is the abstraction of the terminating condition--when the input sequence is exhausted.
		</para>
		<para>
			Direct iteration, such as the <code>while</code> loop above, is impossible with the preprocessor.
			However, the code can be rewritten recursively--which can be mirrored with the preprocessor.
			<snippet>
				unsigned long binary(const char* x, unsigned long r = 0) {
				    return *x ? binary(x + 1, r * 2 + (*x - '0')) : r;
				}
			</snippet>
			It is possible to implement a preprocessor-based version at any of these (not counting the iterative version) levels of abstraction.
			(The following examples all use a <link id="string"/> data structure to specify bits.)
		</para>
		<para>
			Direct translation of the recursive version requires a much more detailed understanding of how <link id="recursion"/> is generalized in Chaos.
			For the sake of comparison, it is listed here:
			<snippet>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-add.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-demote.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-mul.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-control-iif.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-recursion-basic.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-recursion-expr.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-string-core.h/>
				
				#define BINARY(string) BINARY_S(<STATE/>(), string)
				#define BINARY_S(s, string) \
				    <EXPR_S/>(s)(BINARY_I( \
				        <OBSTRUCT/>(), <NEXT/>(s), string, (0) \
				    )) \
				    /**/
				#define BINARY_INDIRECT() BINARY_I
				#define BINARY_I(_, s, string, x) \
				    <IIF/> _(<STRING_IS_CONS/>(string))( \
				        <EXPR_S/> _(s)(BINARY_INDIRECT _()( \
				            <OBSTRUCT/> _(), <NEXT/>(s), \
				            <STRING_TAIL/> _(string), \
				            <ARBITRARY_ADD/> _( \
				                <ARBITRARY_MUL/> _(x, (2)), \
				                (<STRING_HEAD/> _(string)) \
				            ) \
				        )), \
				        <ARBITRARY_DEMOTE/> _(x) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				
				BINARY(1 0 1 0) // 10
			</snippet>
			This version is the lowest-level, and, as such, it is likely the most efficient.
			However, the code is dominated by code to emulate <link id="recursion"/> rather than code to calculate the value of a binary literal.
		</para>
		<para>
			A cleaner implementation can be designed if the level of abstraction is increased.
			The next step up from low-level <link id="recursion"/> is the use of a higher-order looping construct, such as <WHILE/>, which eliminates the need to deal with <link id="recursion"/>.
			<snippet>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-add.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-demote.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-mul.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-array-elem.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-control-while.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-facilities-as_args.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-recursion-expr.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-string-core.h/>
				
				#define BINARY(string) BINARY_S(<STATE/>(), string)
				#define BINARY_S(s, string) \
				    <ARBITRARY_DEMOTE/>(<ARRAY_ELEM/>( \
				        1, \
				        <EXPR_S/>(s)(<WHILE_S/>( \
				            s, \
				            PRED <AS_ARGS/>(2), \
				            OP <AS_ARGS/>(2), \
				            (2, (string, (0))) \
				        )) \
				    )) \
				    /**/
				
				#define PRED(s, string, x) <STRING_IS_CONS/>(string)
				#define OP(s, string, x) \
				    (2, ( \
				        <STRING_TAIL/>(string), \
				        <ARBITRARY_ADD/>( \
				            <ARBITRARY_MUL/>(x, (2)), \
				            (<STRING_HEAD/>(string)) \
				        ) \
				    )) \
				    /**/
				
				BINARY(1 0 1 0) // 10
			</snippet>
			This version, as far as clarity is concerned, is much better than the raw recursive version.
			However, there are still a few annoyances.
			The state on which the loop operates includes both the <link id="string"/> of bits and the running result.
			This means that the operation has to operate on both in order for the predicate to eventually yield <code>0</code>.
			Likewise, when the loop does terminate, the result is both the nil <link id="string"/> and the <link id="arbitrary-precision value"/> that holds the result.
			Thus, the actual result must be extracted (in this case, with <ARRAY_ELEM/>).
		</para>
		<para>
			All of these annoyances can be eliminated if the level of abstraction is increased yet again.
			The next step up is to use a higher-order algorithm that generalizes the notion of accumulation--which is also known as "folding."
			In this example, the algorithm of choice is <FOLD_LEFT/>.
			<snippet>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-algorithm-fold_left.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-add.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-demote.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-mul.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-recursion-expr.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-string-core.h/>
				
				#define BINARY(string) BINARY_S(<STATE/>(), string)
				#define BINARY_S(s, string) \
				    <ARBITRARY_DEMOTE/>( \
				        <EXPR_S/>(s)(<FOLD_LEFT_S/>( \
				            s, OP, (<STRING/>) string, (0) \
				        )) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				
				#define OP(s, bit, x) \
				    <ARBITRARY_ADD/>( \
				        <ARBITRARY_MUL/>(x, (2)), (bit) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				
				BINARY(1 0 1 0) // 10
			</snippet>
		</para>
		<para>
			The above example eliminates the problems associated with the template-based approach.
			It unifies the syntax by eliminating the need for groups of bits, it minimizes the "maximum value" problem, and it avoids the "octal literal" issue.
			However, this implementation has its own drawback--the binary literal itself must be encoded in a <link id="string"/> data structure (e.g. <code>1 0 1 0</code> as opposed to <code>1010</code>).
			That isn't too terrible, but it isn't ideal.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="An Alternative Approach">
		<para>
			Maybe the idea of having groups of bits isn't such a bad idea after all.
			It is possible to support groups of bits with the preprocessor as well.
			Such a syntax would look something like
			<snippet>
				BINARY(10101010 10101010)
			</snippet>
			The major drawback of this approach is that it requires 256 macros (for eight-bit groups) to transform a group into something that can be processed.
			Beyond that, the main problem is that <code>10101010 10101010</code> (and similar) is not a valid <link id="string"/> because each element has more than one character.
			In fact, it isn't any library-defined data structure.
			Thus, the special form must be manually converted (using a set of 256 macros) before the result can be accumulated.
			This is accomplished with a <WHILE/> loop that transforms each "element" into a <link id="string"/>.
			<snippet>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-algorithm-fold_left.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-add.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-demote.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-mul.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-config.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-control-while.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-detection-is_nullary.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-facilities-split.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-logical-compl.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-recursion-expr.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-string-core.h/>
				
				#if <VARIADICS/>
				
				#define BINARY(x) BINARY_S(<STATE/>(), x)
				#define BINARY_S(s, x) \
				    <ARBITRARY_DEMOTE/>( \
				        <EXPR_S/>(s)(<FOLD_LEFT_S/>( \
				            s, ACC, \
				            (<STRING/>) <SPLIT/>( \
				                0, \
				                <EXPR_S/>(s)(<WHILE_S/>( \
				                    s, PRED, OP,, x \
				                )) \
				            ), \
				            (0) \
				        )) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				
				#define ACC(s, bit, x) \
				    <ARBITRARY_ADD/>( \
				        <ARBITRARY_MUL/>(x, (2)), (bit) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				
				#define PRED(s, r, x) \
				    <COMPL/>(<IS_NULLARY/>(x())) \
				    /**/
				
				#define OP(s, r, x) \
				    r <SPLIT/>(0, BYTE_ ## x), <SPLIT/>(1, BYTE_ ## x) \
				    /**/
				
				#define BYTE_00000000 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0,
				#define BYTE_00000001 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1,
				#define BYTE_00000010 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0,
				// ...
				#define BYTE_11111111 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1,
				
				BINARY(00000101) // 5
				BINARY(10001000) // 136
				BINARY(11111111) // 255
				BINARY(11111111 00000000) // 65280
				
				#endif
			</snippet>
			(The <code>BYTE_</code> boilerplate can be pre-generated with a small program such as the following:
			<snippet>
				#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
				#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;
				
				void byte(int depth) {
				    static char s[9] = { 0 };
				    if (depth == 8) {
				        printf(
				            "#define BYTE_%s %c %c %c %c %c %c %c %c,\n", s,
				            s[0], s[1], s[2], s[3], s[4], s[5], s[6], s[7]
				        );
				    }
				    else {
				        s[depth] = '0';
				        byte(depth + 1);
				        s[depth] = '1';
				        byte(depth + 1);
				    }
				    return;
				}
				
				int main(void) {
				    byte(0);
				    return EXIT_SUCCESS;
				}
			</snippet>
			It isn't included here because it results in 256 macro definitions--which would waste space without providing further illumination.)
			This implementation has a couple of properties that are good and a couple that are bad--depending on perspective.
			It forces each element to be a full eight bits--which is a primitive form of validation.
			The main concern with the above is that it wastes time doing the conversion from the special form to a <link id="string"/>.
			For a small number of groups, this overhead isn't too bad, but perhaps it can be eliminated altogether....
		</para>
		<para>
			The central point of the following implementation is that a separate special form conversion can be avoided if a new data type is defined--in which case it is no longer a special form.
			The following code first implements a data structure <code>XS</code> (which stands for "extensible string") and then implements <code>BINARY</code> on top of that.
			The <code>XS</code> data structure is similar to a <link id="string"/> except that elements can be identifiers or numbers that are greater than a single character provided an appropriate "expander" is defined.
			For example,
			<snippet>
				#define EXPANDER_abc (a b c)
				#define EXPANDER_xyz (x y z)
				
				XS_HEAD(abc xyz) // a
				
				<CAST/>(
				    <STRING/>, (XS) abc xyz \
				)
				// (<STRING/>) a b c x y z
			</snippet>
			This data structure is extensible in the sense that user-defined "expanders" can be easily written.
			For example,
			<snippet>
				#define EXPANDER_Paul (P a u l)
				#define EXPANDER_Mensonides (M e n s o n i d e s)
				
				#define OP(s, x) <TO_UPPER/>(x)
				
				<EXPR/>(<TRANSFORM/>(
				    OP, (XS) Paul _ Mensonides
				))
				// (XS) P A U L _ M E N S O N I D E S
			</snippet>
			Given such a data structure definition (and the appropriate <code>EXPANDER_xxx</code> definitions), input such as <code>10101010 10101010</code> can be processed directly.
			The potential downside is that the primitive validation has been lost because the <code>XS</code> data type is perhaps <em>too</em> extensible for this purpose.
			<snippet>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-algorithm-fold_left.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-add.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-demote.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-mul.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-cat.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-control-iif.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-detection-is_nullary.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-detection-is_unary.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-logical-compl.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-recursion-expr.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-string-core.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-tuple-rem.h/>
				
				#define XS XS
				#define XS_TAG(tag) tag
				#define XS_NIL() <STRING_NIL/>()
				#define XS_CONS(xs, x) x xs
				#define XS_HEAD(xs) <STRING_HEAD/>(EXPANDER(xs))
				#define XS_TAIL(xs) <STRING_TAIL/>(EXPANDER(xs))
				#define XS_ITEM(x) x
				#define XS_IS_CONS(xs) <COMPL/>(XS_IS_NIL(xs))
				#define XS_IS_NIL(xs) <IS_NULLARY/>(xs())
				
				#define EXPANDER(xs) \
				    <IIF/>( \
				        <IS_UNARY/>(<PRIMITIVE_CAT/>(EXPANDER_, xs)) \
				    )( \
				        <TUPLE_REM_CTOR/>( \
				            1, \
				            <PRIMITIVE_CAT/>(EXPANDER_, xs) \
				        ), \
				        xs \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				
				#define BINARY(xs) BINARY_S(<STATE/>(), xs)
				#define BINARY_S(s, xs) \
				    <ARBITRARY_DEMOTE/>( \
				        <EXPR_S/>(s)(<FOLD_LEFT_S/>( \
				            s, ACC, (XS) xs, (0) \
				        )) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				
				#define ACC(s, bit, x) \
				    <ARBITRARY_ADD/>( \
				        <ARBITRARY_MUL/>(x, (2)), (bit) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				
				#define EXPANDER_00000000 (0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0)
				#define EXPANDER_00000001 (0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1)
				#define EXPANDER_00000010 (0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0)
				// ...
				#define EXPANDER_11111111 (1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1)
				
				BINARY(00000101) // 5
				BINARY(10001000) // 136
				BINARY(11111111) // 255
				BINARY(11111111 00000000) // 65280
			</snippet>
			(The <code>EXPANDER_</code> boilerplate can be pre-generated with a small program such as the following:
			<snippet>
				#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
				#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;
				
				void expander(int depth) {
				    static char s[9] = { 0 };
				    if (depth == 8) {
				        printf(
				            "#define EXPANDER_%s (%c %c %c %c %c %c %c %c)\n", s,
				            s[0], s[1], s[2], s[3], s[4], s[5], s[6], s[7]
				        );
				    }
				    else {
				        s[depth] = '0';
				        expander(depth + 1);
				        s[depth] = '1';
				        expander(depth + 1);
				    }
				    return;
				}
				
				int main(void) {
				    expander(0);
				    return EXIT_SUCCESS;
				}
			</snippet>
			It isn't included here because it results in 256 macro definitions--which would waste space without providing further illumination.)
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Summary">
		<para>
			Without language support, there is no perfect solution to binary literals.
			This article provides a few different ways that they can be specified, each with various drawbacks, but no one solution is ideal.
			Luckily, the purpose of the article isn't to solve that problem completely.
			Rather, the problem is merely an example that can be used to illustrate preprocessor metaprogramming methodology and to exercise Chaos.
			Binary literals, though convenient, aren't really all that useful.
			However, if one knows how to use the tools and techniques available, there is very little that cannot be done.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Postscript">
		<para>
			The astute reader might notice that there is nothing particularly special about binary literals (as opposed to literals of other bases).
			The runtime model might look something like the following:
			<snippet>
				#include &lt;ctype.h&gt;
				#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
				#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;
				
				unsigned long helper(char c) {
				    if (isdigit(c)) {
				        return c - '0';
				    }
				    else switch (tolower(c)) {
				        case 'a': return 10;
				        case 'b': return 11;
				        case 'c': return 12;
				        case 'd': return 13;
				        case 'e': return 14;
				        case 'f': return 15;
				        default:
				            return exit(EXIT_FAILURE), 0;
				    }
				}
				
				unsigned long convert(const char* x, int base) {
				    if (base &gt; 16) exit(EXIT_FAILURE);
				    unsigned long r = 0;
				    while (*x) (r *= base) += helper(*x++);
				    return r;
				}
				
				int main(void) {
				    printf(
				        "%lu\n%lu\n%lu\n%lu\n",
				        convert("ff", 16),
				        convert("123", 10),
				        convert("00000010", 2),
				        convert("00000010", 8)
				    );
				    return EXIT_SUCCESS;
				}
			</snippet>
		</para>
		<para>
			The preprocessor version can be extended accordingly.
			<snippet>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-algorithm-fold_left_aux.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-add.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-demote.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-literal.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-arbitrary-mul.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-cat.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-recursion-expr.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-string-core.h/>
				#include <chaos-preprocessor-string-to_upper.h/>
				
				#define CONVERT(string, base) CONVERT_S(<STATE/>(), string, base)
				#define CONVERT_S(s, string, base) \
				    <ARBITRARY_DEMOTE/>( \
				        <EXPR_S/>(s)(<FOLD_LEFT_AUX_S/>( \
				            s, OP, (<STRING/>) string, (<ARBITRARY_LITERAL/>(base)), (0) \
				        )) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				
				#define OP(s, digit, base, x) \
				    <ARBITRARY_ADD/>( \
				        <ARBITRARY_MUL/>(x, base), HELPER(digit) \
				    ) \
				    /**/
				
				#define HELPER(digit) \
				    <CAT/>(HELPER_, <TO_UPPER/>(digit)) \
				    /**/
				#define HELPER_0 (0)
				#define HELPER_1 (1)
				#define HELPER_2 (2)
				#define HELPER_3 (3)
				#define HELPER_4 (4)
				#define HELPER_5 (5)
				#define HELPER_6 (6)
				#define HELPER_7 (7)
				#define HELPER_8 (8)
				#define HELPER_9 (9)
				#define HELPER_A (1)(0)
				#define HELPER_B (1)(1)
				#define HELPER_C (1)(2)
				#define HELPER_D (1)(3)
				#define HELPER_E (1)(4)
				#define HELPER_F (1)(5)
				
				CONVERT(f f, 1 6)           // 255
				CONVERT(1 2 3, 1 0)         // 123
				CONVERT(0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0, 2) // 2
				CONVERT(0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0, 8) // 8
			</snippet>
		</para>
	</section>
</document>
