<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- **************************************************************************
     *                                                                        *
     *    (C) Copyright Paul Mensonides 2003-2004.                            *
     *                                                                        *
     *    Distributed under the Boost Software License, Version 1.0.          *
     *    (See accompanying file LICENSE).                                    *
     *                                                                        *
     *    See http://chaos-pp.sourceforge.net for the most recent version.    *
     *                                                                        *
     ************************************************************************** -->

<document id="Strings" author="Paul Mensonides" date="2003-2004">
	<section>
		<para>
			A <link id="string"/> is a data structure consisting of a series of space-separated letters, numerals, or underscores.
			For example,
			<snippet>
				a b c
			</snippet>
			is a <link id="string"/> containing three elements, <code>a</code>, <code>b</code>, and <code>c</code>.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <link id="string"/>-specific primitives are located in the <code>chaos/preprocessor/string</code> subdirectory.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Restricted Domain">
		<para>
			<link id="Strings"/>, unlike other data structures, have a restricted domain of possible element values.
			Each element <em>must</em> be a single letter (from <code>a</code> to <code>z</code> or from <code>A</code> to <code>Z</code>), a numeral (from <code>0</code> to <code>9</code>), or an underscore (<code>_</code>).
			Any other character is invalid, and any operation that inserts an invalid character invalidates the <link id="string"/>.
			The invocation of an algorithm on an invalid <link id="string"/> is undefined and will likely cause catastrophic failure.
		</para>
		<para>
			Note that it <em>is</em> safe to use the core <link id="string"/> operations defined in <chaos-preprocessor-string-core.h/> with invalid <link id="strings"/> provided that the invalid element is never the first element of the <link id="string"/>.
			For example,
			<snippet>
				<STRING_HEAD/>(a xyz b) // a
				<STRING_TAIL/>(a xyz b) // xyz b
				
				<STRING_HEAD/>(xyz b)   // invalid
			</snippet>
			This allowance makes it possible to reuse the <link id="string"/> data type in the creation of, for example, and extensible string data type.
			However, such use requires extreme care.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Using Strings as Generic Data Structures">
		<para>
			<link id="Strings"/> can be used as <link id="generic data structures"/> if the the <chaos-preprocessor-string-core.h/> header is included.
			For example,
			<snippet>
				<CONCAT/>((<STRING/>) C h a o s) // Chaos
			</snippet>
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Nil Strings">
		<para>
			In C (prior to C99) and C++, there is no such thing as a nil <link id="string"/>.
			However, the special value <code><STRING_NIL/>()</code> can be used to indicate a nil <link id="string"/> to the core <link id="string"/> operations defined in <chaos-preprocessor-string-core.h/>--thus allowing the generic algorithms to operate on nil <link id="strings"/> in a temporal fashion.
			The other <link id="string"/>-specific primitives, on the other hand, do not recognize <code><STRING_NIL/>()</code>.
			Therefore, a "would-be" nil <link id="string"/> result from a <link id="string"/>-specific primitive is undefined.
			The result of generic algorithm that yields a nil <link id="string"/> is well-defined provided that it is used only as a <link id="generic data structure"/>--meaning that it can be passed to other generic algorithms, etc.--or used by the core operations in <chaos-preprocessor-string-core.h/> after the type prefix is stripped.
			For example,
			<snippet>
				<APPEND/>(
				    <DROP/>(3, (<STRING/>) a b c),
				    (<STRING/>) x y
				)
				// (<STRING/>) x y
			</snippet>
		</para>
		<para>
			In C99, nil <link id="strings"/> are well-defined as "nothing", which is accepted as the representation of nil by all <link id="string"/> primitives.
		</para>
	</section>
</document>
